Narrator: Do you enjoy maths or does it freak you out? If the latter, you’re not alone.
Maths anxiety is the negative emotional response we encounter when dealing with maths.
The fear is real, and it is widespread.
In the UK, around 36% of all 15- to 24-year-olds reported feeling anxious about maths,
compared to only 10% of people aged over 65.
But some maths enthusiasts are determined to change this.
They want to understand the causes of maths anxiety and,
just like the mathematicians they are, want to find a solution. People like Bobby Seagull.
Bobby: Hello, my name is Bobby Seagull.
I’m from East Ham in the London Borough of Newham,
and I’m a part-time school maths teacher,
as well as doing a doctorate in maths education at Cambridge University.
I also present, er, TV programmes for the BBC.
I write a lot of puzzles for BBC Radio 4, I write for the Financial Times,
and I’m an ambassador for the National Numeracy Agency,
as well as being the current UK Libraries Champion.
Narrator: By anyone’s standard, Bobby has an impressive CV.
He studied mathematics at Oxford and London universities
and also has a postgraduate degree from the University of Cambridge.
He worked in the financial sector,
and as a national campaigner for improving maths literacy as a qualified maths teacher.
Bobby became a social media and TV celebrity after he appeared for Cambridge University
on the notoriously difficult BBC quiz show University Challenge,
where his team reached the semi-final. Bobby’s lively personality and huge enthusiasm shone out,
and this gave him an opening into a varied career: not only teaching maths,
but writing, broadcasting, and campaigning to help build ‘maths confidence’.
Maths comes easy to people like Bobby. After all, they’re born with it, right?
Bobby: People often ask me, when I was born, emerging from my mother’s womb,
did I come out and say, ‘I love mathematics.’
I can confidently say that wasn’t the case.
Um, but as a four- or five-year old, I did find a natural affinity with the subject.
But actually later on, when I was about eight or nine, in primary school,
that I really developed my love for the subject. But it didn’t happen in the classroom.
So, I used to collect football stickers, er, like many children back in the mid-90s. I remember,
there was a conversation where a friend said
that a player called Matthew Le Tissier from Southampton was a better footballer than Ian Wright.
And when I asked him why, he just crossed his arms and said, ‘Just because.’
So, people will often make assertions without any evidence.
So, these sticker books actually were treasure troves of information.
It contained names, ages, heights, goals scored, left foot, right foot of the players.
I took all the data from these players and input it into a really basic version of a spreadsheet,
did a quick comparison between the two players and told my friend actually,
Ian Wright is a more effective player on the field. And my friend said,
‘Bobby, you’ve got a good point.’ It didn’t make me more popular,
but it did show me the power of maths, and from that age, I was hooked.
Narrator: One thing that Bobby thinks is vital for getting children into maths is a belief in their own ability,
which can often depend on their teacher.
Bobby: A good maths teacher, I believe,
has confidence in their students because if a student gets something wrong,
if a teacher suddenly puts their hand on their heads and go, ‘Oh God, what have you done?’,
then that child is going to lose their own ability to believe in themselves.
A good teacher will be someone that will encourage them, but at the same time,
try to bring the subject to life.
I know that there are many students who look at maths and think,
‘Oh, what’s the point of the subject? When am I going to use it?’
A good teacher can actually show students actually in the real world, we do use maths.
Narrator: Bobby himself has been teaching maths at a school for over five years
and still teaches part-time. So how does he get his students to enjoy maths?
Bobby: To get students to enjoy maths, one element is something called gamification,
where young people nowadays, they love the idea of competitions and games.
And again, if they use social media apps they’ll try and get streaks on Snapchat
where they respond to each other every day.
So, if you can capture that a little bit…
Again, with my students, we use apps and games where at the end of a lesson,
we might have this, er, challenge where five questions,
er, options A to D, students work in twos or threes.
And then I’ll put the question up, and they’ve got to quickly as a team work out the answer.
And as each answer comes up on the board, they can see their leaderboard position.
So, obviously, it’s not for everyone, some students prefer a sort of lack of competition,
but something like that, where you try and capture students’ outside interests,
because they love games, and you bring it into the classroom.
Narrator: Bobby also believes strongly that children need to understand how maths is relevant
in daily life, to see the practical application of classroom maths in the real world.
Bobby: Some people think that maths is something that you leave at the school gates at 16.
And of course, again, you look at the theoretical aspects of maths like plotting graphs,
perhaps you won’t use that beyond 16.
But every adult will be using maths in some way.
Again, whether you’re thinking about a holiday and checking your foreign exchange,
or whether you’re sometimes helping children’s homework,
or whether you’re going to the bank and trying to get a loan,
or you’re looking at your car and seeing whether the deal you’ve got for one particular deal
is better than another; you are making maths comparisons all the time.
Narrator: And Bobby is determined to show just how often we use maths,
even if we don’t know we’re doing it.
Bobby: So, here we are, in the middle of London, a high street.
It’s really busy, you can see lots of cars, the iconic double-decker red bus going past us,
lots of people, lots of traffic.
If I went and spoke to someone here on this high street and asked them,
‘Do you use maths on a day-to-day basis’, a lot of people might actually say,
‘No, you know, I used maths in school for Pythagoras and trigonometry, but on a day-to-day, no.’
But actually, I tell them,
‘Everyone here is using maths because everyone here is travelling to get somewhere.’
A lot of us go to work and many of us who go to work, commute, by taking public transport.
And imagine you’ve got a job interview, and your bus normally takes 30 minutes.
Again, you might think on a normal day, you might just leave 30 minutes.
But actually, you might need to leave 15 minutes of waiting for the bus.
And because we’re in busy London, lots of buses, there might be delays, breakdowns,
you add, let’s say an additional 15 minutes. It takes an hour.
And that conversation that we’ve had is actually practical maths in everyday use.
And you might think it’s just intuition, but you are using numbers to plan your journey,
like all these people here.
They’ve all got somewhere to be, whether it’s lunch or going to a work meeting,
or picking up some shopping.
All of them are planning and using numbers as part of their journey.
So, the next time someone says to you, ‘I don’t use maths’ – yes, you do.
All of us use maths in everyday life.
Narrator: So, does Bobby think, provided they get the right support,
that anyone can be good at maths?
Bobby: At school, I get many students and, in fact, parents at parents’ evenings, who will tell me,
‘Oh, I couldn’t do maths at school and maybe my son or daughter’s picked up that maths brain.’
But I always think about it, when parents are at the hospital with their newborn children,
and a nurse comes around checking vitals, like, er, two legs, two feet, two arms, two eyes,
they never go, oh, there’s no maths brain.
We’re not born with a maths brain.
I think it’s our experiences in life, in school,
outside in the real world that make us think that we can or can’t do maths.
And then it becomes a cycle of virtuosity, or a sort of vicious cycle where you get things right,
you get encouraged, you work harder, and then obviously,
you develop competence and confidence in the subject or the other way around,
where you make mistakes, then you get scared of the subject, then you avoid it.
And then of course, you become someone that’s not confident and competent in the subject.
Narrator: Bobby has written a book called The Life-Changing Magic of Numbers
and is also studying for a doctorate at the University of Cambridge
on the topic of ‘mathematical anxiety and phobia’.
But whether it’s in the academic world, in the classroom, or in the media,
Bobby has made it his mission to banish the myth of the bad maths brain
and ease that feeling of maths anxiety.
By becoming a maths ambassador, by making the subject fun and accessible,
he’s proving that everyone can understand – and enjoy – the world of mathematics.